MAY 9TH 1940.
HITLER HAS INVADED CZECHOSLOVAKIA,
POLAND, DENMARK, AND NORWAY.
3 MILLION GERMAN TROOPS ARE NOW POISED
ON THE BELGIUM BORDER, READY TO CONQUER
THE REST OF EUROPE.
IN BRITAIN, PARLIAMENT HAS LOST FAITH
IN IT'S LEADER, NEVILLE CHAMBERLAIN.
THE SEARCH FOR A REPLACEMENT
HAS ALREADY BEGUN.
Order!
Mr. Speaker!
Leader...
Order!
The Leader of the Opposition,
Clement Attlee!
Mr. Speaker.
It seems that I have not
been clear enough.
Then let me leave no doubt
about my feelings regarding
Mr. Chamberlain’s future
as Prime Minister.
Will I right, honourable gentlemen?
Be quiet!
Owing to his years of inactivity
and incompetence,
we find him personally responsible.../
Incompetence!
Personally responsible for leaving
this nation ruinously unprepared
to face the present Nazi peril.
Order!
Order!/  Shame. Shame.
We are at war, Mr. Speaker.
At war.
And leaving aside whether he is
fit to be a leader in peace-time.
He has proven himself
incapable of leading us in wartime.
Order!
I said order!
Therefore, in the national interest,
we the Opposition,
are willing to enter into
a Grand Coalition with the “ruling”
Conservative Party, so-called...
Order!
But not, and I stress, never under
the leadership of Mr. Chamberlain
who has lost
the confidence of this House!
In the country’s interest man, resign!
Step down! And let us find a new leader!
Shame on you!
Shame! Shame on you!
Where is Winston?/ Ensuring his
fingerprints aren't on the murder weapon.
Order!
As the Opposition refuse to join
a government headed by me,
we must now select my successor.
Someone with
new stands to form
a coalition government.
I will step down tomorrow.
But...
I didn't want my own party, the gentlemen
I most respect, to know first.
Yes.
It must be Halifax./  Yeah, yeah.
There’s no question!
Our Foreign Secretary.
Halifax./  Yeah, of course.
No contest! Halifax.
Thank you, gentlemen, I appreciate
your confidence however my time
has not yet come.
Then who?
About on whomever the task may fall,
he shall be required
to explore every avenues.
Including better Diplomatic talks.
Indeed.
Towards the restoration
of peace in Europe.
Absolutely./  Yeah, yeah.
Well, gentlemen, there is
only one candidate,
only one man that
the Opposition will accept.
Oh, no.
Oh, surely not./  Completely no.
No, no, no.
Not now, this is totally absurdity.
And if he stretches out his hand
and says, “Gimme”,
you need to anticipate what he wants,
black pen, red pen, paper, or “Clop”,
that’s his hole punch.
"CHAMBERLAIN TO RESIGN”
CHURCHILL EXPECTED TO BE NEW PREMIER
How selfish to resign, time like this.
D’you think they’ll take me
to Downing Street? To get the job?
Not after that Spotted Dick
you served last week, eh?
He mumbles, so it’s almost
impossible to catch everything.
And be prepared to type fast,
short bursts and double-spaced,
he hates single-spaced, hates it!
Good luck.
To the French Ambassador.
With German forces,
crossing into Holland,
Holland alone...
Come on, telegram!
Holland alone,
request reassurance,
that French forces will now move,
move at once,
to...
To protect Belgium.
Stop.
French ambassador, sir.
Monsieur Ambassador!
Ah. They’ve already invaded Belgium.
Holland and Belgium.
I will convey your plea to
the Prime Minister at once.
Yes...
The situation is still very confused.
Yes.
Goodbye.
"To the French ambassador."
"With German..."/  Scrap that.
New telegram.
To General Ismay...
In the...
What is it now?!/  Your son.
Randolph, quickly.
No, last night they said I might be
made Prime Minister today.
But that was yeterday.
Let's see what happens today.
Let's see what...
Let's see what Neville does today.
Yes.
Thank you, my boy.
Yes, keep buggering on!
Now...
To General Ismay./  Ah, General Ismay.
Sawyers, get rid of this, will you?
To General Ismay.
In the light of today's events,
the time is
ripe
for many preparations
to be...
Are you...
Striking those keys in a normal fashion?
It’s awfully loud,
I can’t hear myself think!
Read it back.
"To General Ismay."
"In the light of today's events,
the time is right..."
Ripe! Not "right"!
God's teeth girl!
I said ripe!
Ripe - ripe-ripe-ripe!
The last sentence...
"The-the time is ripe."
For.../  "For..."
For.../  Many... many... many...
Many, many, many, many...
How many “many”s did you
write in your compound?!
One "many"! For...
For many preparations.../
"For many preparations...
...to be.../  ...to be made."
Single-spaced! Single-spaced!
Were you not briefed, young lady?
Single-spaced?
Someone set it on single-spaced.
And...
Then why did you persist?!
I...
Tell Evans to send me someone
who can get it right
the first time! Go, out! Out!
Ripe!
T-T-T!
He shouted at you.
Did he shout at you?
No./  He can be an awful brute.
I-I made too many mistakes.
I think you were nervous.
And he has a knack
for drawing out the very worst in
those trying to help him the most.
Oh it’s not him. It’s me.
He’s... he’s...
He's a man.
Like any other.
Come on...
Dear?
The War Cabinet has been called.
The bloody cat is under the bed again.
My darling...
May I tell you something that
I feel you really ought to know?
I’ve noticed a recent deterioration
in your manner.
You’re not so kind as you used to be.
You became rough, sarcastic,
over-bearing and rude.
Is this about the new girl?
If the King asks us
to become Prime Minister...
We don’t know that.../
I don’t want you to be disliked.
More than I already am?
My darling, you're on the brink,
of having tremendous power,
surpassed only by the King.
With such power you really
must try to be more kind.
And if possible, calm.
I want others to love
and respect you, as I do.
Telegram for Mr. Churchill.
This is the BBC Home Service.
Here is a short news bulletin.
The German army invaded Holland
and Belgium early this morning.
By land and land parachutes.../
There's a telegram.
The Armies of the Low Countries
are resisting.
An appeal for help has been made
to the Allied governments.
And Brussels says.../
It’s from the Palace.
...the Allied troops are
moving to their support.
100 warplanes were seen over Brussels,
and it's now reported that
in the first raid over Brussels,
several hundred people
were killed and injured.
And several buildings
have been destroyed.
Thank you.
Miss...?
Layton.
You're shaking./  So are you!
You from excitement, I from terror.
You've been wanting this
your entire adult life.
No, since the nursery.
But do the public want me?
It’s your own Party to whom
you’ll have to prove yourself.
I’m getting the job only
because the ship is sinking.
It's not a gift, it's a revenge.
Let them see your true qualities.
Your courage...
My poor judgment./  Your lack of vanity.
My iron will./  Your sense of humor.
Ho Ho Ho!
Now go!/  Go?
Be.../  Be what?
Be yourself.
Myself?
Which self should I be today?
One should have had power
when a young man,
when wits were sharp, sinews strong.
Oh, well. Lead on, MacDuff.
When youth departs,
may wisdom prove enough.
Hardly seems like
there’s a war on at all.
You know I've never ridden a bus?
Sir?
I've never queued for bread.
I believe I can boil an egg
but only because I've seen it done.
The only time I tried to
ride the Underground,
was during the General Strike.
Clemmie dropped me
at South Kensington station.
I went down but I got lost,
and came straight back up.
It was awful.
Why not Halifax?
I favour Halifax.
I wanted Halifax.
The Lords wanted Halifax.
Perhaps Halifax wanted Halifax.
Then why have I been forced
to send for Churchill?
Because he's the only
member of our party,
who has the support of the Opposition.
His record is a litany of catastrophe.
Gallipoli, 25,000 dead.
The India Policy. Russian Civil War.
The Gold Standard.
The-the-the Abdication.
And now this...
Norway ‘adventure’.
What, eighteen hundred men?
One aircraft carrier, two cruisers,
seven destroyers and a submarine.
Winston lacks judgement.
He was right about Hitler./ But even
a stopped clock is right twice a day.
First Lord of the Admiralty,
Mr. Winston Churchill!
Early.
Keen.
I accept your resignation,
but I want you to know, how
cruelly I think you’ve been treated.
Thank you, Your Majesty.
This way, my Lord.
Your Majesty./  Mr. Churchill.
I believe you know
why I have asked you here today.
Sir, I simply cannot imagine why.
It is my duty to invite you to take up
the position of Prime Minister
of this United Kingdom.
Will you form a Government?
I will.
Very well.
That was... quite easy.
Yes, it was.
I believe we are to meet regularly.
Once a week, I'm afraid.
How was...
How if Monday?
I shall endeavour to be available,
on Mondays./ Four o’clock?
I nap at 4.
Is that... permissible?
No. But necessary.
I work late.
Then perhaps lunchtime?
Lunch?
Mondays.
Your Majesty.
Prime Minister.
Greetings, gentlemen.
Mr. Churchill, welcome to number 10.
Thank you, sir.
Mr. Churchill, what's your agenda?
Agenda?
A glass of Pol Roger.
Come here, Sir!/
You have your pictures.
Prime Minister.
Anthony.
How was the King?
Anxious.
He's never forgive me for supporting his
brother's marriage
to Wallis Simpson.
You only have to meet him once a week.
That’s like saying you only
have to have your tooth pulled
once a week.
Composition of your war cabinet?
Who should sit on it?
Chamberlain, of course.
And the Reverend “Holy Fox”.
Halifax.
Keeping your enemies close?
Oh, more than that.
Without them, the party
will get rid of me.
Oh! And that sheep
in sheep’s clothing, Attlee.
Come on Daddy, everyone’s waiting.
I'll be there in a jiffy, my love.
I heard that before you were asked,
they offered it to Lord Halifax.
No, I doubt that.
Halifax would never turn it down.
He's the fourth son of an Earl.
Fourth sons turn nothing down.
I only wish the position had come
your way in better times, sir.
You have an enormous task ahead of you.
My only hope it's not too late.
I am very much afraid it is.
But we can only do our best.
Hip hip.../  Hurray!
Hip hip./  Hurray!!
Good heavens, what a frightful sight!
Oh, a toast!/  Yes, a speech!
Yes./  The bottle.
Come here./  Yes.
My darling husband...
Some of you might not know of it.
On the eve of our marriage
I got “cold feet”,
but as I’d already called off
two engagements
by the age of 21, I was in danger of
gaining a reputation for being a ‘bolter’,
and it would’ve been
poor form to call off a third!
Hear hear./  Lucky for Daddy.
But the real reason for my
wintry feet was because I knew,
even then,
that his priority would be public life.
It worried a young girl greatly
this wretched thought of
eternally coming second.
But so it has proven to be.
And in due course our children
would have to make their peace
with this same fact.
We all did, you see.
In our own ways.
And now, today,
we all received our reward,
proof that our small sacrifice
was for a far, far greater good.
I give you, your father,
my beloved husband,
the Prime Minister.
Prime Minister!
Here’s to...
To not buggering it up.
"To not buggering it up!"
Belgium was a ploy.
They punched through
the Ardennes into France
and crossed the Meuse in under 24 hours!
No-one can cross
the Meuse River in 24 hours.
Apparently the Germans can.
Look to Chamberlain's handkerchief.
If he waves it at the end
of Churchill’s speech,
we show approval.
If not, keep quiet.
The Prime Minister!
Here we go.
Mr. Speaker.
On Friday evening last,
I received His Majesty’s commission
to form a new administration.
It was the evident wish and will
of Parliament, and the Nation,
that this should be conceived
on the broadest possible basis,
and that it should include all parties.
Yes.
A War Cabinet has been convened...
No...
Correction.
Has been formed.
"Formed."
A War Cabinet has been
formed of five members,
representing with
the Opposition parties,
and the unity of the Nation.
Read.
The three party Leaders
have agreed to serve,
either in the War Cabinet
Or in high executive office./
...or in high executive office.
With this agreement's in placed,
I now invite the House by the
resolution which stands in my name,
to record it's approval, and to declare
it's confidence in the new government.
Miss?
I’m coming out in a state of nature!
It must be remembered
that we are in the preliminary stage
of one of the greatest
battles in history
and that many preparations
have to be made here at home.
Sir, I take up my task
with buoyancy and hope
and say to the House,
as I said to those who have
joined the government.
I have nothing to offer,
but blood, toil, tears and sweat.
We have before us an ordeal
of the most grievous kind.
We have before us many,
many long months of struggle
and of suffering.
You ask, what is our policy?
I say it is to wage war by sea,
land and air, with all our might
and with all the strength God
can give us,
to wage war against a monstrous tyranny
never surpassed in the dark and
lamentable catalogue of human crime.
That is our policy.
If you ask, what is our aim?
I can answer in one word.
Victory.
Victory at all costs.
Victory, in spite of all terror.
Victory however long and
hard the road may be.
For without victory,
there can be no survival.
Contempt.
Well, you have to start somewhere./
Well, you have to start somewhere.
Snap.
Our policy is to wage war.
At all costs.
No survival.
Good God, he is incapable of even
pronouncing the word peace,
let alone entering into negotiations.
Awful, the thought
that I shall never see
my country at peace again.
I have cancer.
Oh, Neville.
Winston must be removed from office.
If we can get him to declare
that he refuses to even consider
peace negotiations with Germany,
then you and I will perhaps
have clear grounds to resign.
that will force a vote
of “no confidence”.
The party couldn't count for that,
you’re the chairman for heavens sake.
He’ll be finished.
And would you agree
to be Prime Minister?
Well...
With Winston out of the way who can say.
But the important thing, Neville,
is that your policies
would be back on the table.
Peace and the protection of our nation.
On record.
I beg a pardon?/
He must declare on record
his refusal to engage in peace talks.
We must have it in writing.
WAR OFFICE, LONDON
CHURCHILL WAR ROOM - PASS
Thank you.
Miss Layton./  Good morning.
Follow me.
Good morning./  Thank you, sir.
Thank you, madam.
What goes on down here?
That’s a need to know. And you don’t.
The lavatory?/  For the PM’s use only.
Sleeping quarters, for
when you miss the last train.
Come.
That's the map room.
No women allowed./
What department is this?
Indiscretion in conversation,
or any other form,
within or without these rooms
regarding what happens here
is a statutory offense and
punishable by up to two years
imprisonment with hard labour.
Clear?/  Crystal.
Good.
That's the War Cabinet room.
Never...
I Don’t mean to be rough on you but...
Them's the rules.
This is the typists room.
Good morning, sir./  Ladies.
And here’s you.
Belgium and Holland
may fall in any hour.
The French?
The entire French ninth army,
some two hundred thousand men
have capitulated.
All of them?!
Capitulated. Deserted.
It was a rout.
All our land forces, roughly
300,000 men, are now in full retreat.
Air-cover? For our troops?
The Luftwaffe control the skies.
We simply don’t have
enough planes to challenge them.
In fact, I strongly recommend we stop
sending our precious fighter-planes
to be wasted in France.
Save them for our own defence.
And our navy sits idle,
neutralized, useless.
Our fleets no sooner
come within their range,
than we come under
blistering air attack.
Their speed is devastating.
Panzer tanks. Plunging rapidly
westward, through the centre.
But they will have to
pause for fuel supplies.
This is not the last war, Sir.
Their tanks can stop for fuel
at a petrol station.
Petrol station?
The road to Paris now lies open.
7 million refugees are on the move.
Collectively we are looking at the collapse
of Western Europe in a few days.
Should the public be told?
Not yet.
First, we must rouse our old friends
to an heroic resistance.
France must be saved.
Premiere.
[ Prime Minister ]
"Although our situation...
...is very serious."
"It's not the first time...
...that we are...
...facing...
...a crisis...
...together."
Perhaps in English, Prime Minister.
We have survived
crisis before, and I am...
I'm confident we will survive this one.
Tell me how you plan to counter-attack.
There is no plan.
You must counter-attack!
You... you must...
"You must...
...fight!"
"It must!"
I do not believe this...
This...
Panzer breakthrough is a real invasion.
Not a real invasion?/  No...
As long as their tanks are not
supported by infantry units.
They are merely little flags,
stuck on the map,
because the tank crews
cannot support themselves.
No, I refuse to see
in this spectacular raid
of the German tanks, a real invasion!
He's delusional.
Completely delusional.
He's English!
He is an actor.
In love with the sound of his own voice.
Oh I love to listen to him,
but we must never take his advice.
Has a hundred ideas a day.
Four of them are good,
the other 96 downright dangerous.
His father used to say,
a great orator, but...
Until he lost his mind to syphilis.
How nations suffer...
...for the sins of their fathers./
My opinion?
At this critical juncture
for the empire,
we have a drunkard at the wheel.
Wakes with a scotch,
bottle of champagne at lunch,
another at dinner,
brandy and port till the wee hours...
I wouldn’t let him borrow my bicycle!
He’s a Conservative
who defects to the Liberals,
lobs grenades at us for 10 years,
then flops Conservative again,
as it bloody suits him!
Sorry, but he stands for one thing,
himself!
We might have to replace him, Bertie.
Replace him?
We must strive for peace,
so every son and daughter of this land
could emerge from this crisis
with something recognisable as 'home.'
Spoken like a true Prime Minister.
"V" for victory.
Sir, you need to reply
to the Lord Privy Seal.
Yeah, yeah...
Tell the Lord Privy Seal,
I’m sealed in the Privy.
And I can only deal with one
shit at a time.
The broadcast is tonight, so...
Don’t spare me, Anthony...
Be frank.
I don't think so.
You don’t think so, what?
You’re suggesting we’re somehow winning.
We’re not.
No but...
it will inspire them.
Winston, I know.../  Anthony, Anthony.
I am going to imbue them
with a spirit of feeling they don’t
yet know they have!
You asked my opinion.
I caution against it.
Cicero.
Cicero!
"...and if fortune is adverse...
...something, something..."
It's not here... I leave it here.
Clemmie!
Cat!
We cannot pay the bills./
My copy of...
...Cicero. Did you shelve it?/
Did you hear what I said?
What was that?/  We're broke.
Oh...
Out!
Come on! Everybody out!
I dare not write another cheque.
Well, I’ll economise.
Only four cigars a day!
You’re insufferable!
Anything else?
Yes.
My love for you./  Oh!
How much have you had
to drink this morning?
I see you now
as I first saw you
in 1904.
And I simply stood, speechless.
I must have been very beautiful
to have achieved that miraculous effect.
Four years till we saw each other again.
They went by in an absolute flash.
You didn’t lack for admirers, your...
"Loyal attendant" in Sidney Peel.
Brilliant man./  Lionel Earle.
Wonderful dancer.
And then at Lady St Hellier’s
dinner party,
who should show up?
Pig.
Just the same.
Are we terribly old?
Yes. I’m afraid you are.
Oh, you're beast!
I'm...
Will you hear me read my speech
for tonight’s broadcast?
Prime Minister! Prime Minister,
the situation in France,
is it true we're in full retreat?
Is France lost?
Above the bench is the champ's goat,
under the bench is the crack's goat.
If you will sit here, at your desk.
And speak slowly and clearly.
Into the microphone.
So...
If you're ready,
on the stroke of 9
the light will come on and
we shall go live to the nation.
Nine o'clock.
Red light.
You begin.
Yes?
One moment.
Prime Minister.
Are we ready?
I...
One moment, one moment...
We are going live./
One moment, damn you!
And...
...four,
...three,
...two,
...one.
I speak to you for
the first time as Prime Minister,
in a solemn hour for
the life of our country,
of our Empire,
of our allies,
and above all,
of the cause of Freedom.
A tremendous battle is raging
in France and Flanders.
The Germans, by a remarkable combination
of air bombing
and heavily armored tanks,
have broken through the French defenses
north of the Maginot Line,
and strong columns
of their armoured vehicles
are ravaging the open country...
Which for the first day or two,
was without defenders.
However...
I have invincible confidence
in the French Army and it's leaders.
Only a very small part
of that splendid Army
has yet been heavily engaged,
only a very small part of France
has yet been invaded.
Side by side,
the British and French peoples
have advanced.../  Advanced?
...to rescue not only Europe,/
How bloody dare he!
...but mankind
from the foulest and most
soul-destroying tyranny
which has ever darkened and stained
the pages of history.
But now one bond unites us all,
to wage war
until victory is won,
and never to surrender ourselves
to servitude and shame,
whatever the cost
and the agony may be...
Conquer we must,
as conquer we shall.
Well done, sir.
Oh, I thought you did marvelously.
For the last ten years I was
the only one who told them the truth.
Until tonight.
There's no advance.
It's a shambles.
We're in full retreat.
But would you be serving them tonight
by denying them sleep, and...
Terrifying their children?
Even if the terror is coming?!
Because the terror is coming.
There is time enough for the truth.
Have you seen this?
What’s so funny?
Prime Minister.
Sir./  Yes. What is it?
Perhaps...
Look, I'm...
I'm not sure if you know this but...
The way you are doing
your V for Victory sign.
Well, in the poorer quarters,
that gesture means something else.
What does it mean?/
I wouldn’t like to say, sir.
I was captured by the Boer,
I spent time in a South African prison.
Up yer’ bum.
Sir.
Up yer’ bum?
Up yer’...
The way you do it, sir. Yes sir.
But if you turn it around, that's fine.
Wouldn’t like millions of people
to take it the wrong way.
Oh, I see!
Up yer’ bum!
Your Majesty.
Don’t wish to take too much
of your time.
I heard you on the wireless.
Was I comprehensible?
The public need to be led,
not misled, not left to work
it out for them-themselves.
Right.
Will that be all, Your Majesty?
Yes. Good day Prime Minister.
Good day.
I believe I’ve just recieved
a royal rap on the knuckles.
As of 2200 hours last night,
the Germans have
encircled sixty British,
Belgian and French divisions.
On our part all our forces
under Lord Gort,
have now withdrawn, or are trying
to withdraw to the French coast,
to Dunkirk.
...where we cannot reach them./
How many of our men are trapped?
All of them.
Our country's entire
professional soldiery.
And we can see
no clear way to rescue them.
General, are you telling me
that we shall have lost
the entire British army
by the next few days?
That’s correct.
The German force is
superior in every regard
and are only fifty miles from the coast.
They are pushing us into the sea.
No, the Germans must not reach the sea.
Not before we evacuate our men.
Ismay? What have you got for us?
As it stands, I cannot see
we have much hope of getting any
of our forces out in time.
Not a man?
No, I mean, we cannot be so
totally at their mercy!
What is our next step?
Anyone?
Come on! Speak!
We still have a Garrison at Calais.
25 miles to the west.
How many men do we have there?/
4,000. More or less.
Why didn't you say so?
Yes, then we have them go east,
engage with the German
columns moving on Dunkirk.
Buy us some time.
Draw the Nazi focus away from Dunkirk
whilst we execute a maritime
evacuation of our forces.
Is that possible?/
It would mean a huge sacrifice.
Four thousand young men!/
To save 300,000!
Under whose command
is the Calais Garrison?
Brigadier Nicholson./  Very well.
Tell Nicholson that it is of the
greatest importance to this island,
that his garrison draw the enemy’s,
tanks and artillery and
bombers away from Dunkirk.
Invite their wrath and...
Well, to fight on
if needs be...
If needs be until
the destruction of his command.
It's suicide.
Prime Minister.
I have reservations.
Who is free of reservations?
About an unnecessary sacrifice
when there is available alternative.
What an alternative?
Italy have offered
to mediate peace talks
between ourselves and Germany.
I already indicated that
provided the liberty
and independence of
British Empire were assured
we will consider any proposal.
With... with Hitler.
Holding the whip hand,
do you really think he would honour
our liberty and independence?
It would be in
his interest to do so, sir.
Because.../  The only thing to do
is to show that maniac
that he cannot conquer
this island, and for that
we need an army.
General, tell Brigadier Nicholson
the Germans must not reach the sea!
Not before we get our boys off that
bloody beach!
I take full responsibility.
Really?/  Really! Yes, sir!
It is the reason I sit in this chair!
Well, surely before you
take full responsibility
of the death of 4,000 men,
you wish to consider
every available avenue.
What is this?!
What is your mind on the
principle of peace talks, sir?
Do we take it for example, that
you preclude yourself
from even considering
taking part in such negotiations?
I should like to speak
to Viscount Halifax
and Mr. Chamberlain alone.
Issue the order to the Calais Garrison.
Confirm it has been done.
Dismiss.
You too. Come on, out.
Bridges! You, come on, hop it!
Out! Out!
Winston. We are facing
certain defeat on land.
The annihilation of our army
and imminent invasion.
We must be rational.
We are a sea-going nation.
Have been since the Bronze Age.
The Channel is ours,
our moat, our battlement
and the German doesn’t recognise
an expanse of water
greater than a bloody lake!
They have first to reach
this island, Edward.
Where are men, women, and children,
whom we will have failed
despicably, in our duty of protection
will be entirely defenceless./
And who's fault is that?
Against the largest army
the world has ever seen
Furthermore, once France falls,
Germany can concentrate
on aircraft production
and they will then have
the French fleet as well.
What is to stop Hitler then, Winston?
Words? Words? Words alone?
If you will not permit
any talk of peace then I
shall be forced.../
Might we not allow Edward
simply to meet the Italian
ambassador, Bastianini,
discuss their possible role as mediators
between us and Germany,
and find out their price?
Sir.
Mr. President.
Winston!
Franklin!
How are you?
Fine. Fine.
How are you, Prime Minister?
Oh, I'm in fine, Franklin...
Listen...
I'm telephoning about your...
Navy ships.
If you could to loan us just
50 older Destroyers.../
Ah, yes.
Even 40 would do.
Well, I...
I did ask around,
but just not possible I’m afraid.
The Neutrality Act we signed
last year has tied my hands.
Just can’t swing it.
I tried./  Then, can I...
Do I have your permission
to send an aircraft carrier
to pick up the P-40 fighter planes
we purchased from you?
Mr. President?
You got me there again.
New law preventing trans-shipment
of military equipment.
But we’ve paid for them.
We... we've paid for them
with the money that we...
That we borrowed from you.
I'm so, so sorry, Winston.
I need not impress upon you with
trouble faced by the Western Hemisphere.
Without your support, in some fashion..
I know. I know.
You are on my mind day and night.
Look.
We could, possibly...
Mr. President.
I mean to say...
We are facing the gravest odds.
We could take your planes
to about a mile from
the Canadian border,
and then if you send across
a team of horses from Canada,
nothing motorized,
then you could pull 'em
over the border yourself.
How does that sound?
Horses?
You did say “a team of horses”?
Well, I guess you could
push ‘em yourself.
The damn things have wheels.
Up to you.
We could do that, Prime Minister.
Prime Minister?
Anything you can do at this time
would be most welcome.
Goodnight to you, Winston.
It must be late there.
In more ways than
you could possibly know.
Prime Minister.
Get me Admiral Ramsay on one of these.
Yes, Prime Minister.
Winston to Admiral Ramsay.
Admiral Ramsay!
It’s the Prime Minister.
Bertie?
Bertie.
I hope I didn’t wake you.
Not at all.
I was just reading the Bible.
Exodus?
Listen, Bertie, we need
to evacuate our boys.
The Navy is saying that with one cruiser
and six destroyers, and with the
Luftwaffe controlling the skies above,
we'll be lucky to get 10% out.
I want you to order
an assembly of boats.
Boats?
Yes...
Civilian boats.
As many as you can get your hands on.
Longley's clipper,
Fearnley's gin palace,
anyone with a pleasure craft bigger
than 30 foot that can get to France.
Bertie, you still there?
All right.
Help me stage this thing, Bertie.
We must at least try to bring
some of our boys home.
I will have the BBC issue the order.
Good.
Bertie, you still there?
Sir?
We need a name, for this operation.
Good morning, Prime Minister.
Prime Minister, do you have
anything to explain this morning?
Prime Minister, Mr. Jefferson...
Prime Minister.
Prime Minister!
Prime Minister are you.../
Prime Minister! Wait!
How do you manage
drinking during the day?
Practice.
I...
Should like to discuss.
I have been asked if
plans should be drawn to
evacuate myself... my family to Canada.
I would like to know the opinion
of our Prime Minister.
My opinion would be that you must do
what you feel is right for yourself,
your family,
and the nation.
Your survival is paramount.
Prime Ministers,
we seem to come and go
at an astonishing rate.
Your position in Parliament...
I'm told isn't strong.
My party,
resents in the way
Chamberlain was pushed aside.
And many others doubt me.
They want Halifax still.
But why get rid of the organ grinder
and replace him with the monkey?
Lord Halifax is a close
personal friend of mine!
I'm unwanted.
I’ve never been trusted
since the Gallipoli campaign.
Unwanted.
Perhaps it's because you scare people.
Who?
You scare me.
What?! What nonsense.
What could possibly be scary about me?
One never knows what is going to
come out of your mouth next.
Something that will flatter,
something that will wound.
My emotions are unbridled.
A wildness. In the blood.
I share it with my father.
My mother also.
We lack the gift of temperance.
Were you close to your parents?
My mother was glamorous.
But perhaps too widely loved.
My father was like God.
Busy elsewhere.
Good day, gentlemen.
I’ve asked the Minister for War
to join us.
Neville, you sit on there.
Anthony.
Obviously, we are in
a dangerous situation.
But I am assured by the French Premiere
that while some
German tank units have reached the sea,
the situation generally seems
to be well in hand.
What news from Calais?
The Garrison attacked,
but was forced back,
and is now surrounded on all sides.
They are being shelled
and bombed mercilessly.
Casualties are at sixty percent.
Prime Minister.
The question of peace talks.
We must hold our nerve.
Signal only that we're intend
to fight it out into the end.
A peace offer telegraphs
our weakness./  Agreed.
And even if we were beaten,
we should be no worse off than we should be
if we were now to abandon the struggle.
Let us therefore avoid
being dragged down
the slippery slope
with talk of a negotiated peace.
Slippery slope?
The only.../
I suspect Italy and Germany...
The only slippery slope.../  ...want to
get us so deeply involved in negotiations
that we should be unable to turn back.
Nonsense! Bastianini informed me...
I propose.../
The only slippery slope...
Will you stop interrupting me
while I am interrupting you?!
When I chose my War Cabinet,
I took great care to surround
myself with old rivals.
I may have overdone it.
Viscount Halifax,
the approach you proposed is...
It's not only... it's futile,
but involves us in a deadly danger.
The deadly danger here is this
romantic fantasy of fighting to the end.
What is “the end”?
If not the destruction of all thing?
There is nothing heroic
in going down fighting
if it can be avoided.
Nothing even remotely patriotic
in death or glory
if the odds are on the former.
Nothing inglorious in trying
to shorten a war
that we are clearly losing./  Losing?
Europe is still.../  Europe is lost!
And before our forces
are wiped out completely,
now is the time to negotiate,
in order to obtain the
best conditions possible.
Hitler would not interests to insist
on outrageous terms.
He will know his own weaknesses.
He will be reasonable./
When will the lesson be learned?
How many more dictators must be
wooed, appeased...
Good God, given immense privileges,
before we learn.
You can’t reason with a tiger
when your head is in it's mouth!
Prime Minister!
Winston!
Yesterday you gave permission for.../
What permission?
For me to meet Bastianini.
I sanctioned theoretical exploration.../
Theoretical?
...of what price Italy would ask.
Nothing more. I did not sanction.../
If you will not allow any further
exploration of a peace agreement,
then you will have my resignation.
Oh, don’t be absurd.
I need you, Edward, you know I do./
I will not stand by
to watch another generation of young men
die at the bloody altar of your hubris!
And you would have us die as lambs!
Was Gallipoli not enough for you?
How dare you!
Our troops were chewing
barbed wire in Flanders!
And I saw it!
Opening a second front,
outflanking the Turks was
a serious military idea and
it could’ve damn-well worked if
if the Admirals and the First Sea Lord
hadn’t dithered away
our element of surprise!
The choice is yours, Winston.
You have 24 hours to enter
into peace talks, or I resign.
I told him.
It shook him.
Imagine it did.
Gave him 24 hours.
I don’t expect him to agree,
so I should resign first.
You then follow.
That’s critical if we are to trigger
a revolt to new confirm of the House.
I should announce it.
The King will back us.
Prime Minister.
I wonder if we might schedule you
to address the Outer Cabinet?
Today, the Admiralty have made
an Order requesting
all owners of self-propelled
pleasure craft,
between 30' and 100' in length,
to send all particulars
to the Admiralty, immediately.
To Brigadier Nicholson.
30th Infantry Brigade.
Calais.
Every hour
you continue to exist
is of the greatest help
to our forces at Dunkirk.
Have the greatest
possible
admiration
for your splendid stand.
Your evacuation however
will not take place.
I repeat...
Will not take place.
Signed.
Here.
Here!
May I be excused?
You may not!
What is this about?
No one tells us anything.
It’s all classified.
We hear scraps and it’s worse
than knowing nothing.
What would you like to know?
How many men will survive?
Come with me.
I’m not allowed in the Map Room./
You are now.
Prime Minister.
Prime Minister./  At ease, gentlemen.
Now.
The German army controls
every French port,
except Dunkirk, here, and
Calais, here to the west,
where the garrison
under Brigadier Nicholson,
is drawing fire and delaying
the German advance on Dunkirk.
At both points,
our troops are encircled.
We’re still trying to
clear Dunkirk harbour,
of wrecked ships so we can
then land the boats we need
to get our boys off those beaches, but
enemy aircraft is
attacking us constantly.
Our only hope in Dunkirk is
thick cloud cover
to thwart these attacks,
but the skies remain clear.
Even then,
I am told we will need
a miracle to get even
10% of our men out.
Courage, Miss Layton.
Courage.
General.
How long have they got,
if we don’t rescue them?
One,
maybe...
Two days.
News from Calais.
The 13th Infantry, sir.
They’ve retreated to the town’s citadel.
As a last and probably hopeless stand.
The order “Everyman for himself"
has been given.
Brigadier Nicholson, there's
a telegram, sir./  Thank you.
All right.
Let's do this, well done.
All right, man?/  All right.
Your evacuation however
will not take place.
I repeat, it will not take place.
CALAIS FALLEN.
NUMBERS OF DEAD OR CAPTURED UNCERTAIN.
SIGNED BY GENERAL GORT.
Go to bed, Pig.
You must sleep.
Leave me, Clemmie.
The opportunity for doing so
passed a long time ago.
Operator.
How do I direct your call?
Get me Ramsay./  One minute.
Bertie?/  Sir?
What’s been the response?
It will take time.
It’s too soon to judge.
How many boats so far?
Winston, it will take time.
The request for civilian boats, Bertie,
was not a request.
It was an order!
Miss Layton./  Sir.
I need to reach...
To reach...
Speak to...
To?
3pm.
3pm, sir?
Yes.
Yes. Ask Bridges to summon the uh...
The War Cabinet at 3pm. Thank you.
Sir.
From Lord Gort, in France, sir.
Belgium has fallen.
They will surrender at midnight.
France will soon follow suit.
We have received reports that
the most probable method attack
which Germany might employ
against this country
is a large fleet of fast motor boats,
possibly up to 200,
carrying 100 men apiece
to carry out a seaborne raid
on a large scale.
By this means a considerable
force of the enemy
could be landed
at many points on the coast
simultaneously with
air-borne raids inland.
We do not feel that
by naval or air action
we could prevent such a landing.
Could you repeat that?
We must prepare for the imminent
invasion of our island.
We recommend that
the country should be warned
and drawn to
the immediate danger,
and that all personnel
require to put Britain
in a state of defense should be
mobilized. Wtihout a moment delayed.
Lights.
Thank you.
General.
That all...
preparations be made.
Let the record state I have received
word from the Italian Embassy in London.
Italy is prepared
to mediate a resolution
between Britain, it's allies,
and Germany.
Perhaps... then...
The time for such an offer from us is...
is when...
Is when Germany has made
an unsuccessful attempt
to invade this country.
Unsuccessful?/
Then you leave me no other option
to offer.../  Winston! Winston!
You are refusing
to grasp the realities of
how precarious our position is!
Our entire army
is about to be wiped out.
Terms!
Must! Be struck!
Anthony?
Then it seems...
We have no choice,
but to at least consider the
path
of negotiation.
If Hitler's peace terms are...
Overlordship of Central Europe
and return of certain
German colonies...
A-a-and...
If he will leave us
our independence,
then I'll be greatful
to get out of our present
difficulties.
It's quite unlikely
that he will make such an offer,
but if I were told what
the German terms were,
then I would be prepared
to consider them.
Thank you, Prime Minister.
We shall prepare a draft
memorandum at once.
I have come to wonder,
in recent days,
whether it was
part of my duty...
Part of my...
Part of my duty, yeah.
To consider...
Whether it was...
Will that be all for tonight, sir?
Whether it was part of my duty.
Entering into...
Into negotiations with...
HITLER DEFIANT
RUTHLESS IN ATTACK
that...
that corporal...
No.
That tyrant...
Monster of wickedness...
Butcher... that...
That monstrous...
Savage.
Bloodthirsty guttersnipe!
Housepainter...
HOUSEPAINTER!
Where were we?
Well?!
I didn’t understand you, sir.
You were...
Were?
You were mumbling.
Mumbling.
The... the... the right words...
Wouldn't come.
They will come, sir.
No one compared
what's together like you.
Your beau?
My brother.
Where is he now?
He was falling back on Dunkirk.
But he never made it.
What?
I'm just looking at you.
Shall I read back what we have?
Yes. Yes please.
I have come to wonder in recent days
whether it was my duty to consider
entering into negotiations
with...
With...
I just couldn't standing... imagining
never being here anymore.
Whether is because I am no longer alive,
or the palace itself is gone.
Canada.
You must decide, sir.
You could rule in exile./  Truly...
...is that to be my fate?
You know something
I’m aware in this moment?
Still in hate-grade.
Bloody angry.
Darling?
Winston, Darling?
There's someone to see you.
You have a visitor.
My darling, you’ve the full weight
of the world on your shoulders.
I.../  No, I know, I know.
But these inner battles
have actually
trained you
for this very moment.
You are strong because
you are imperfect.
You are wise because you have doubts.
Now, should I let him in?
Who?
The king.
Which King?
Our King?
Well if it isn’t him, it’s
a most impersonation.
Mr. Churchill.
I hope you can forgive
the late our hours.
Your wife thought tonight
would be a good time.
Shall we sit?
Oh... oh, yes...
Please.
Something to drink? Perhaps?
I...
received...
a visit...
From?/  Viscount Halifax.
It appears the prospect of a peace deal
has increased
dramatically.
The war cabinet is drafting a letter
to Mussolini,
asking him to broker talks
with Herr Hitler.
Then Halifax
was correct?
I should like to know your mind.
It would be helpful to know yours first.
Mine? I should like to know it myself.
Nations
which go down fighting rise again,
and those
which surrender tamely are finished.
Belgium?
Collapsed.
Norway?/  Holland.
France any hour.
And the mood of Parliament?/
Fear. Panic.
And you?
Are you not afraid?
I am most terribly.
Support in the War Cabinet,
for a campaign of resistance
has collapsed.
Later today, I will address the House
accordingly.
You have my support.
Your Majesty?
I confess I
had some reservations
about you at first, but
while some in this country
dreaded your appointment, none...
None dreaded it like Adolph Hitler.
Whomever can strike fear
into that brute heart
is worthy of all our trust.
We shall work together. You shall
have my support. At any hour.
Beat the buggers.
Now I'm going to Parliament,
but without support in my own party.
I must sue for peace.
You once gave me some advice.
Perhaps I can give you some.
Go to the people.
Let them instruct you.
Quite silently, they usually do.
But tell them the truth. Unvarnished.
If invasion is imminent,
then our troops in France are lost,
they must be prepare.
On certain matters,
I have value few people with whom I can
talk,
frankly.
Perhaps now we have each other?
And I no longer scare you?
A little.
I can cope.
We are ready.
More or less.
More or less what, Bertie?
Give me a number.
In total 860 vessels.
The biggest civilian fleet
ever assembled.
Operation Dynamo waits on your command.
Admiral...
Initiate Dynamo.
And may God watch over them all.
We’ve lost the Prime Minister!
Do you know how to
use this thing?/  Yes, sir.
How do I get to Westminster?
Westminster?
The District Line. East.
One stop.
District Line. East. One stop.
That doesn’t sound so hard./  No, sir.
Thank you.
Thank you, sir.
The Memorandum is titled
“Suggested Approaches to Italy”
for is as follows.
“If Signor Mussolini
will co-operate with us
in securing a settlement
of all European questions, which
safeguard the independence
and security of the allies,
and could be the basis
of a just and durable peace for Europe.”
“We will undertake at once to discuss
with the desire to find solutions,
the matters in which Signor Mussolini
is primarily interested.”
“We understand
that he desires the solution
of certain Mediterranean questions
and if he will state in secrecy
what these are,
France and Great Britain
will at once do their best
to meet those wishes.”
So...
This is the Underground!
Thank you.
Does anyone have a match?
What are you all staring at?
Have you never seen a Prime Minister
ride on the Underground before?
What is your name?
Oliver Wilson, sir.
And what do you do Mr. Wilson?
Brick-layer, sir./  Ah!
Brick-layer! We shall have
great need of brick-layers soon.
Business will be looking up!
Progress!
How old?
Five months, sir.
He looks like you.
Madam, all babies look like me.
What is your name?
Mrs. Jessie Sutton./  Ah, Mrs. Sutton!
What a pleasure.
Abigail.
Abigail Walker.
Marcus Peters.
"Marcus Peters."
Agnes Dillon./  "Agnes."
Maurice Baker./  "Mr. Baker."
Alice Simpson./  "Alice Simpson."
Miss Margaret Jerome.
Ah, Jerome!
My mother was a Jerome!
I expect we are closely related.
Please, please, sit.
Sit everyone.
Thank you, Mr. Baker.
So how are you all...
How are you all bearing up?
Good... good spirits?
Yes.
Just as well.
We still need them.
Let me ask you all something,
this thing, a weighing on my mind.
Perhaps you can provide me
with an answer.
You...
The British people.
What is your mood?
Is it...
Is it confident?
Yes./  Confident. How confident?
Very.
Some people say it’s a lost cause.
Lost cause is the only ones
worth fighting for.
Too late./  Yes...
Now let me ask you this.
If the worst came to pass,
and... and the enemy were
to appear on those streets above,
what would you do?/  Fight!
Fight the fascists!/  Fight them with
anything we can lay our hands on!
Broom handles if we must!/
Street by street!
They'll never take Picadilly!
Never take Picadilly indeed!
And what if I put it to you all
that we might,
if we ask nicely
get very favourable
terms from Mr. Hitler,
if we enter into a peace deal
with him right now?
What would you say to that?
Never!/  Never!
So... never.
Never.
Will you never give up?
No, never!
"Then out spake brave Horatius."
"The Captain of the gate:
To every man upon this earth,
Death...
...cometh soon or late."
"And how can man die better
than facing fearful odds?"
"For the ashes.../
"For the ashes of his fathers,
and the temples of his gods."
Are you crying?
Crying?
Yes, yes, crying.
I blub a lot, you know?
I think you'll have to get used to it.
What... What stop is this?
Westminster, sir.
Westminster?
It's my stop.
Prime Minister!
Sir!
The War Cabinet...
Sir! They're waiting.
I'm due to address the Outer Cabinet.
What?/  Now!
I haven’t spoken to them since
the formation of the new government.
Prime Minister./  Good day, gentlemen.
I'm about to speak to
my Outer Cabinet in my rooms
and I extend the invitation to any
of you who would care to join them.
Let's go.
This afternoon, I will address the House
on the matter of our nation’s security.
At this very moment,
the War Cabinet is drafting papers
that lay out our willingness
to enter into peace talks
with Herr Hitler, via his...
His lacky, Mussolini.
I have thought very carefully
in these last days,
whether was part of my duty,
to consider entering into
negotiations with...
With that man.
Then I...
I spoke with them.
Oliver Wilson.
Mrs. Jessie Sutton.
Mrs. Abigail Walker.
Marcus Peters and Maurice Baker.
Alice Simpson and Miss Margaret Jerome.
Brave, good, true citizens
of this kingdom, and they argued
strongly, that it was idle to think
if we tried to make peace now,
we should get better terms
than if we fought it out.
The Germans,
Mr. Baker felt,
would demand
in the name of disarmament
our naval bases, and much else.
And I think he's right.
Jessie Sutton, speaking for many,
believes we would then become
a slave state,
though a British Government
which would be Hitler's puppet.
A government set up under...
Under Mosley or some such person./
No, no!
And I join with them
in asking a further question,
a question I now put to you:
Where should we be
at the end of all that?
Perhaps some might benefit.
And the powerful might be able
to parlay good terms,
preserved in their country redoubts,
out of sight of the Swastika
flying on the... over
Buckingham Palace./  Never!
Over Windsor,
and they draped on these very buildings.
Never!/  Never!
So I come to you...
I come to you,
to learn your minds
in this grave hour.
You see, it was pointed out to me
by my new friends,
that you might even rise up
and tear me down
were I for one moment
to contemplate parley or surrender.
Were they wrong?
No!/  No!
Were they wrong?/  No!
Were they wrong?
No!/  Thank you, thank you...
Then I'm hear you...
I am hear you!
It appears to be your will also,
that if this long island story of ours
is to end at last,
then let it end only when each one of us
lies choking in his own blood
upon the ground!
Yeah!/  Bravo!
And when I asked to know their minds,
there occurred a demonstration
which considering
the character of the gathering,
quite surprised me.
There is no doubt,
that if we falter at all
in the leading of the nation,
we should all be hurled out of office.
I am sure now that every Minister
on both sides of the house
is ready to be killed quite soon,
and have all his
family and possessions destroyed,
rather than give in.
In this they represent
almost all the people.
It falls to me in these
coming days and months,
to express their sentiments.
There shall be no negotiated peace.
And you must each do now as you see fit.
Now if you excuse me, gentlemen.
I believe I am tend
to address the Parliament.
And I’m yet to write
a word of my speech.
There’s the buggers.
Tiny!/  Sir.
Miss Layton?/  Sir?
I’m in need of you.
We must both now resign.
Force a vote of no confidence.
Let's go to the Commons first.
Join our colleagues.
And speak after the
Prime Minister’s address.
Here's a woman, who is always tired
for she lived a life
where too much was required.
The Prime Minister!
Turning once again to
the question of invasion,
I would observe that there
has never been a period
in all these long centuries
of which we boast,
when an absolute guarantee
against invasion
could have been given to our people.
I have, myself...
Full confidence,
that if all do their duty,
if nothing is neglected,
and if the best arrangements
are made as they are
being made,
we shall prove ourselves once more able
to defend our island home,
to ride out the storm of war,
and to outlive the menace of tyranny.
If necessary for years,
if necessary alone.
At any rate, that is what
we are going to try to do.
That is the resolve of His Majesty's
government, every men of them.
That is the will of
Parliament and the nation.
The British Empire, and
the French Republic,
linked together in their cause
wand in their need,
will defend to the death
their native soil,
aiding each other like good comrades
to the utmost of their strength.
Yes!/  Yeah! Yeah!
Even though large tracts of Europe
and many old and famous States have...
have fallen or may fall
into the... the...
grip of the Gestapo
and all the odious apparatus
of Nazi rule,
we shall not flag or fail.
We shall go on to the end.
We shall fight in France,
we shall fight on the seas and oceans,
we shall fight with growing confidence
and growing strength in the air,
we shall defend our island,
whatever the cost may be.
Yeah! Yeah!
We shall fight on the beaches,
we shall fight on the landing grounds,
we shall fight in the fields
and in the streets,
we shall fight in the hills.
We shall never surrender,
And if...
which I do not for a moment believe,
this island or a large part
of it were...
were subjugated and starving,
then our Empire beyond the seas,
armed and guarded by the British Fleet,
would carry on the struggle!/  Yes!
Until in God's good time,
the New World, with all
its power and might,
steps forth to the rescue
and the liberation of the old!
Yes! Yes!
Bravo, bravo, bravo!
Hurray!
Very well!
Bravo!
Victory! Victory! Victory!
Changed your mind?
Those who never change their mind
never change anything.
What just happened?
He mobilized the English language
and sent it into battle.
- Manually Adaption by -
\N* H@w-to-kiLL @subscene.com*
ALMOST ALL OF THE
300,000 TROOPS AT DUNKIRK
WERE CARRIED HOME
BY WINSTON'S CIVILIAN FLEET
NEVILLE CHAMBERLAIN DIED SIX MONTHS LATER
VISCOUNT HALIFAX WAS SOON
REMOVED BY WINSTON
FROM THE WAR CABINET
AND SENT TO WASHINGTON
ON MAY 8, FIVE YEARS LATER,
BRITAIN AND ITS ALLIES
WOULD DECLARE VICTORY
LATER THAT YEAR, WINSTON WAS VOTED OUT
OF OFFICE IN THE GENERAL ELECTION
"SUCCESS IS NOT FINAL,
FAILURE IS NOT FATAL.
IT IS THE COURAGE
TO CONTINUE THAT COUNTS."
WINSTON CHURCHILL